Terrence Webster-Doyle Papers 2004.0028
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Terrence Webster-Doyle Papers
1975-2003
2004.0028
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
9.0 Linear feet
Dr. Terrence Webster-Doyle is the author of twenty internationally acclaimed, award-winning books that discuss topics such as bullying, martial arts, and teaching children peaceful solutions to social problems. The collection contains many of his publications, and related materials.
Webster-Doyle, Terrence.
Biography
Dr. Terrence Webster-Doyle is a prolific writer having written over 50 internationally acclaimed, award winning literary works for young people and adults that focus on the issue of achieving peace through understanding what prevents it – conditioned thinking. He has won the prestigious Benjamin Franklin award nine times along with numerous other outstanding accolades for his work in the peace education field. Webster-Doyle's understanding on the nature and structure of conditioned thinking in creating conflict is based on the initial insights of Quantum Physicist Dr. David Bohm, a colleague of Albert Einstein, formerly of Princeton University. A recent outcome of this relationship of creating literary works based on understanding the root causes of violence in conditioned thinking has helped over 5000 Liberian children of war to understand and resolve conflict peacefully. Webster-Doyle's books are archived at the University of Connecticut and are also on permanent display at the International Museum of Peace and Solidarity in Samarkand, Uzbekistan, the Commonwealth of Independent States and at the Hiroshima Peace Memorial Museum, Hiroshima Japan.
Collection Background
Established in 2004, the Terrence Webster-Doyle Papers contain materials having to do with conditioned thinking based on the bully/victim cycle – from the playground to the battlefield – and how the primitive biologically programmed brain creates psychological conditioning that creates conflict and hence prevents peace, individually and globally. Influenced by the educational philosopher Jiddu Krishnamurti in 1968, Webster-Doyle began to teach classes at Sonoma State University in the search for understanding the cause, nature, and structure of conditioned thinking. Webster-Doyle also studied the work of Dr. David Bohm Quantum Physicist, a former colleague of Albert Einstein, who studied the relationship between thought and reality; and Aldous Huxley, author of Brave New World and George Orwell author of 1984 which explored the nature and effect of destructive conditioning.
With his wife Jean, they founded the Atrium Society to promote the understanding of conditioned thinking in the education of young people worldwide (http://youthpeaceliteracy.org). His 56 published literary works contain not only books but also workbooks for students, and curriculum for teachers, martial arts instructors, and parents, with worksheets, group and individual activities, and tools to chart progress in conflict prevention. Webster-Doyle is also the Founder and Chief Instructor of Martial Arts for Peace, and has utilized his extensive experience for over 50 years in this peace educating field as a focus for the exploration of the nature of conflict for individuals, schools and society.
Working with Dr. Marvin Davis, an eminent Liberian peace educator, Webster-Doyle discovered a completely new paradigm for peace education. After carrying out a research test case of twenty former child combatants’ post-war behavior for five years in Buchanan, just after the Liberian civil war’s end, Dr. Davis, using Webster-Doyle’s program Why Is Everybody Always Picking On Us? Understanding the Roots of Prejudice demonstrated that the fundamental cause of the war was due to psychological conditioning. This realization led to the book Brave New Child – Liberating the Children of Liberia and the World. Dr. Davis has now introduced these findings to more than 5000 war-torn Liberian youth with amazing success. Not satisfied that these findings completely addressed understanding the core of human conflict Webster-Doyle’s further studies based on this initial find led to the realization that underneath this psychological conditioned state of mind in the primitive biologically hardwired brain was a genetic instinctual malfunction in the brains of these young warriors. This inbuilt state of mind was rooted in eons of being hardwired for war as a maladaptive survival instinct that was paradoxically preventing it and that was the fundamental cause of the conflict. In other words, they suffered from an inborn conditioned drive to survive through ethnocentric domination, what Webster-Doyle calls “ethnocentric genetic genocide”– that war is in our DNA – that it’s a genetically instinctive survival reaction due to the notion of what survival mistakenly means. What triggers this biological hardwired automatic survival reaction is the instinctive fear of who and what we have been conditioned to think is a threat to “our” survival. In this case of war it is the image of “the enemy,” that ethnocentric ideological nemesis –“them” – that is in competition with “us” for our survival. And that survival at all costs depends on our allegiance to and identity with our group, belief system or nation state for that assurance. This led to the development of Webster-Doyle’s program Hardwired for War – A Genetically Instinctive Survival Reaction http://www.atriumsoc.org/hardwired-for-war.php that is now being used in schools in Liberia. His books are also on permanent display at the International Museum of Peace and Solidarity in Samarkand, Uzbekistan, the Commonwealth of Independent States and at the Hiroshima Peace Memorial Museum in Japan.
Scope and Content
The Collection contains notes, manuscripts and copies of Dr. Terrence Webster-Doyle's publications as well as correspondence, publications, and audio-visual materials associated with his programs and publications. Subjects discussed in the collection include the Atrium Society, the International Journal of Peace Studies, bullying, martial arts, war, the Oak Grove School, and Vermont Peace Day. The collection includes materials that span his literary career, from 1975 to 2003.
Arrangement
Series I: Writings ( undated, 1978-2003 ) includes articles, drafts, illustrations, proofs and manuscript materials.
Series II: Correspondence ( undated, 1975-1995 ) contains general correspondence and correspondence associated with Oak Grove School.
Series III: Subject Files ( undated, 1977-2001 ) includes notes, brochures, articles, announcements and general materials pertaining to Dr. Webster-Doyle's activities, programs and publications.
Series IV: 2012 Addition ( 2011 ) includes correspondence, notes and publications. The series includes materials related to the Atrium Society, the International Journal of Peace Studies, and martial arts programs.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Books
Awareness: Exploring the roots of conflict Dodd D1624
Brave New Child. Education for the 21st Century Dodd B6565
Breaking the Chains of the Ancient Warrior Dodd CLC C3423
Bully Buster System Dodd D1638-1640
Case of the conditioned mind Dodd C 10385/ CD1852
Defeat the Bully without fighting Dodd D 1625/1626
Dr. T's Character for Kids Kit Dodd D1641
Dr. Webster-Doyle's Martial Arts Guide for Parents Dodd B6566
Eye of the Hurricane. Dodd CLC C3424
Facing the double edged sword. Dodd CLC C3425
Fighting the Invisible Enemy. Dodd CLC 3426
Flight of the Golden Eagle. Dodd CLC 3427
Growing Up Sane. Dodd B6567
Karate. The art of empty self. Dodd B6568/B6569/A4968
Martial Arts Manners. Dodd D1642
Martial arts masters. Dodd CLC C3428
Mastering Martial Arts Manners. Dodd D 1627
Maze of the Fire Dragon. Dodd CLC C3429
My first martial arts book. Dodd CLC C3430
Lucha a la Cuerda. Dodd D 1637
One Encounter One Chance. The Essence of the Art of Karate. Dodd C6161/C6162
Operation Warhawks. Dodd CLC C3431
Peace, The enemy of Freedom. Dodd B6570
The Religious Impulse: A Quest for Innocence. Dodd B6571
Respect, the act which conquers fear. Dodd D1629
Respect, the martial arts Code of Conduct. Dodd D1628/CLC C3432
Tug of War. Dodd CLC C3433
Understanding: Creating peace. Dodd D1630-1/2
War: What is it good for? Dodd D1632
Why is everybody always picking on me? Dodd D1633
Why is everybody always picking on us?. Dodd D1634/1635, CLC C3434/3435
The Case of the Conditioned Mind. Dodd C10385
[Russian title]. Dodd CLC C3436
Periodicals
Black Belt, January 1997.
Black Belt Kids
Detskai Interatira [Russian periodical], January - April, June - July 1993.
Journal of Asian Martial Arts, v. 6, #2, 1997.
Shuhari, v. I, #1-2.
Sports Illustrated for Kids, September 1996.
Taking Time, v. I, #3, 11.
VHS
Atrium #2 Dodd Video 193
Black Belt; How to defeat the Bully the smart way 2004-0028.vr1
Charles Grodin Show appearance Dodd Video 184
Education for Peace in the 21st Century Dodd Video 182
Education for Peace Dodd Video 181
Forum 22 show Dodd Video 183
International Children's Disarmament Dodd Video 188
Solving Conflict Peacefully through the Art of Karate 2004-0028.vr2
Audio Cassettes
Dr. Aiello Show 2004-0028.ac2, 2004-0028.ac3, 2004-0028.ac4, 2004-0028.ac5, 2004-0028.ac5, 2004-0028.ac6, 2004-0028.ac8, 2004-0028.ac14
Radio Martial Arts Dodd Audio 865
Warrior Talk 2004-0028.ac1, 2004-0028.ac7, 2004-0028.ac9, 2004-0028.ac10, 2004-0028.ac11, 2004-0028.ac12, 2004-0028.ac13
CDs
Complete Education Dodd
The Case of the Conditioned Mind Dodd CD 1852
Acquisition Information
The Collection was donated to the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center by Terrence Webster-Doyle in February 2004.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Cameron, Rod.; Webster-Doyle, Terrence, 1940-; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Author.; Authors, American--20th century.; Authors, American.; Books.; College teachers--Vermont.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Galley proofs.; Illustrations (visual works).; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Posters.; Press releases.; Publications.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.; Works of Art.
- Series I: Writings, undated, 1978-2003
  - "Action through Intelligence", undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Article, undated (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Awakening the Conditioned Mind, Instructor guide (photcopy), 2000 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - "Being of Nothingness", undated (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Breaking the Chains of the Ancient Warrior
    - Illustrated pages: 20-21, 32-33, 41, 44-45, 48, 56, 64, 68-69, 76, 84-85, 96-97, 104, 112-113, 120-121, 124, 132-133, 140, 146-147, 151, 154, undated (Box OS:, Folder 2)
  - "Bridge Between East and West", undated (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Bullying Conference Proposal, undated, 1992 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - "Creating the Enemy", undated (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - "Defeat the Bully without Fighting", 1993 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - "Enlightenment Knot", undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Eye of the Hurricane
    - Illustrated pages: intro, 16, 20-21, 24, 28, 32, 36-37, 41, 52, 58, 62-63, 75, 82, 88-89, 96-97, 104-105, undated (Box OS:, Folder 3)
  - Facing the Double-Edged Sword
    - Illustrated pages: 2-3, 39, 46, 51, undated (Box OS:, Folder 5)
  - Fighting the Invisible Enemy
    - Illustrated pages: 2-3, 8-9, 12, 20-21, 37, 48-49, 52, 60, 72-73, 88-89, 106-107, 115, 125, 128-129, 145, undated (Box OS:, Folder 4)
  - "Growing Up Sane"--Proposal, undated (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - "Growing Up Sane"--Outline, undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Living Skills Certificated Training Program--Proposal, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - "Living through Thought", undated (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Martial Arts Workshop (Adults) I, III--Leader's Notes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Martial Arts Workshop (Young people) II, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Maze of the Fire Dragon
    - Illustrated pages: vii, 5, 24-25, 29, 32, 36, 40-41, 45, 55, 62-63, 69, 76-77, 84, 96, undated (Box OS:, Folder 7)
  - "Meaning of Intelligence", undated (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Observations, undated (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Operation Warhawks
    - Proof (photocopy), undated (Box 3:, Folder 18)
    - Illustrations, undated (Box 3:, Folder 42)
    - Illustrated pages: 12-13, 16, 24-25, 46, 54-55, 65, 90, 94-95, 104, 116, 130-131, 134-135, 146-147, 151, 154-155, 164, 182-183, 190-191, 203, undated (Box OS:, Folder 1)
    - Illustration proofs, undated (Box 3:, Folder 43)
  - Peace, the enemy of freedom
    - Cover layout, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
    - Photoengravings, 1990 November 16 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
  - "Response-Ability in Relationship", 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Tuff Stuff Program--General Information, undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Tug of War
    - Illustrated pages: 5, 8-9, 16-17, 25, 32, 40-41, 62, 67, 76-77, 84, 96-97, 100, undated (Box OS:, Folder 6)
  - Why Am I Always Picking on Myself? Teacher's Guide (original), 2003 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Why is Everybody Always Picking on Me? Teacher's Guide (photocopy), 2000 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Negatives for covers/jackets, undated (Folder 46)
- Series II: Correspondence, undated, 1975-1995
  - General, undated, 1991-1995 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Oak Grove School, undated (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Oak Grove School, 1975-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Tug of War Russian contract, 1991 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
- Series III: Subject Files, undated, 1977-2001
  - Announcements, articles, clippings, press releases, brochures, undated (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Atrium School, undated (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - Atrium School--Curriculum, undated (Box 2:, Folder 29)
  - Child in Changing Times, undated, 1977-1980 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
  - Childrens Bill of Rights for a Bully Free Society (TM), undated (Box 2:, Folder 31)
  - Defeat the Bully--Level I, undated (Box 2:, Folder 32)
  - Faculty Meeting, 1988 August 11 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
  - Institute of Living Skills, undated (Box 2:, Folder 34)
  - Martial Arts for Peace, undated (Box 2:, Folder 35)
  - Martial Arts in the 21st Century, undated (Box 2:, Folder 36)
  - Notes, undated (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Notes--S.T.A.R. - F.I.G.H.T. (TM), undated (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - Posters, undated (Box OS)
  - Transcript (microcassette), undated (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Transformation of Violence, undated (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - Vermont Peace Day, 1992-2001 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
- Series IV: 2012 Addition, 2011; 0.2 Linear feet
  - Correspondence, fliers, publications, 2011; 0.2 Linear feet Ordered as recieved (Box 2012.0028_1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects include: The Atrium Society, "Hardwired for War: What created this battle in my brain"- Dr. Terrence Webster-Doyle with Adryan Russ, peace studies, "Through the Eyes of Peace: A Story", "Trainings with Dr. Terrence and Jean Webster-Doyle".